It's not often that I get to return back to some of the work that I've this, you know, was in 2015,
was when I made this piece. The work began in 2014. And so I talked about a lot about it,
you know, for a few years, but then it's been a minute since I've returned back to it. So, yeah,
I appreciate the space being made for it. So this piece was made a year after our efforts as a sort of
collage reflection of all of the different organizing pieces that went into We Church genocide.
I think there was multiple, there were so many different stories that came out of We Church genocide.
And I wanted this piece to be a portal for that storytelling and all of the different,
all of the different creative actions and strategies and moments that that came out of the work.
And so in this piece, you know, you see the black silhouettes of the eight of us joining hands with
a few other people. I think actually this is just the eight of us that went to Geneva, Switzerland,
with our report. We Church genocide that was re-uplifting the 1951 We Church genocide, original petition,
that was charging the US with genocide of black people between 1945 and 1951. I think it had
documented over 153 instances of lynchings of black men across the country. And what we wanted to do
in Chicago was lift up genocide as not just this notion of immediate death, but of this slow
progression of not having a grocery store within five miles of a black and brown community,
not having mental health resources, not having, so like the slow death march of
and of policing and of not, you know, resourcing black communities and brown communities. And so
we wanted to lift that up in Chicago around police violence and lifting up the story of
policing as inherently violent, as policing as just like tied to this legacy, this long legacy of
of violence all the way to slave patrol, right? So we were trying to take all of that history and
putting it into like a current context of the violence that young people experienced in Chicago.
And so we took this report that included youth testimonies, it included data, it included all
of these different pieces and took it to the UN. We were the youngest, we were the youngest
group of people who delivered a report to the UN. We broke protocol, we, you know, we
you're supposed to like sit and read your report and ethos vets van lear, who is an incredible
public cultural organizer, like stood up and read their piece as like a poem, as spoken word
poem instead of just like sitting and reading the the top lines of the report. You know, we held
up art in the space. We held up the, so this going back to the silhouette, the silhouette is of us
holding standing up when the US is responding to some of the questions of the UN around
to the use of tasers. And so we, not happy with the US's response, of course, being like,
oh, you know, our police are trained because they, you know, they visit our website and they read
the how-to for how to use tasers. And so they're trained. And we're like, that's not, that isn't,
that isn't it. And so, you know, we, we, um, stood up and held our arms up and
fists up for a while for I think 30 minutes. And security was called, they didn't know what to do,
it had never happened before. So it was, it was a moment. And I think that was like a really
powerful moment to sort of like having the foreground of this piece. And so then in the background
was like sort of all of the like historic and then like moments that led up to that moment
and we church on a site. So like you have, um, in the top right corner, you have CPD killed Deimo
and Reston Pisteimo and Deimo Dominique Franklin was a 23 year old black man who was
tased and died due to the tazing a few days later by a police officer first thing about a
lubricer from a Walgreens. And it was, uh, the, Deimo was a friend of people who went to,
you know, of ethos and people who went to Geneva, friends of friends, um, and community. And so
we carried his name to the UN with us and held up his, his photo and held up his, you know,
and if anything, if it didn't, if it didn't change anything, we were like at least it was a form of,
making space and a container for the grief that community felt, um, and, and gave folks a space to,
you know, to, to share that grief and to feel that grief.
Um, right below it, there was like a, during We Charge, Genocide's efforts, there was a bus ride,
um, to Kalimit City, which is a suburb, um, right outside of Chicago, um, and it says justice for
Stefan, um, and it was a freedom ride to, um, uh, to demand justice for the murder of Stefan Watts,
who was a young black man, uh, killed by police and Kalimit City. Uh, he, um, was a black disabled,
um, man who, um, yeah, was killed by the police and so we, we wanted to make a solidarity, um,
ride out there to, to that area. Um, and then in the top left, you'll see like, um,
Paul Robison, who was one of the original, uh, drafters of We Charge Genocide's report.
There's the reparations fight that was happening in, in, you know, a parallel to We Charge Genocide.
So there's just like a lot in there that I just wanted to offer to, uh, to our communities and to,
and beyond to just sort of, like I said, a portal to storytelling, right, and, and also just to add
historical context, um, and then inspiration and, and, and building sort of like this muscle of hope
that like, this work had happened and we can build upon it and continue the work, um, moving forward.
I think I leaned into facelessness because I wanted, um, and an emity for young people who I
didn't have the consent up to draw and include in these pieces. Um, that was like one, but also I
think it works because for me, I want people to see themselves reflected in the piece and to be
able to place their face on there as they view it being, um, yeah, just like, uh, being this like
space that they can, yeah, see themselves in. Um, and the mediums are our watercolor, um,
and, uh, micro pens, um, ink and, then scanned digital, to digitize digitize and sort of like
enhance the contrasting of the piece, um, was the way I went because sometimes the watercolors didn't
work out in the, in the ways that I wanted them to. I miss them. It's like, I want more pigment.
Um, so yeah, so, and then this stuff I think maybe just a couple of hours to, to create. I remember,
I, I remember sketching it out. I was living actually in the Bay Area at the time, um, sort of like a small,
like the only five months I ever lived outside of Chicago in my life. So I went, um, and had like an
artist, uh, studio there. And it's, yeah, I just remember, you know, sketching this piece and, um,
laying the color on within just a few hours and then, uh, scanning and sending over to Mariam
Kaba. And she was like, I love this piece so much. Let's give it out to everyone who participated.
And then she submitted it to the DuSable Museum. And she was like, it's in permanent collection now.
And I was like, oh, thanks. Thanks. I appreciate that.